A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Special Collections Publications FA1395
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Special Collections Publications
1934-2010
Rockefeller Archive Center
Fund for the Advancement of Education (U.S.)
Fund for Adult Education (U.S.)
Ford Foundation
FA1395
31.4 Cubic Feet 83 boxes - 82 letter document containers and 1 half-legal document container
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas.
During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
The Fund for Adult Education (FAE) and The Fund for the Advancement of Education (TFAE) were established by the Ford Foundation in 1951 as semi-autonomous funds to obtain large-scale results quickly and to help the Ford Foundation avoid violating federal laws which forbade tax-exempt foundations from accumulating "unreasonable" surpluses.
The Fund for Adult Education played a major role in the early development of public television stations and programming with grants totaling more than $11 million. A second major effort of FAE was to develop a series of study-discussion programs as a method of bringing adults together with trained program leaders to discuss such topics as American History, the arts, and world affairs and to create a body of materials that could be published and used nationwide. FAE's final project was "Education for Public Responsibility." FAE made grants of $1.5 million to universities and professional organizations for programs, conferences, and fellowships to prepare young and middle level professionals to face contemporary problems and issues. FAE was terminated in 1961.
The Fund for the Advancement of Education supported new and experimental programs at all levels of formal education. The five areas to which TFAE focused its resources were: the equalization of educational opportunity; improvements in curricula; clarification of the functions of educational institutions; improvement of educational management and financing; and the improvement of teaching. TFAE operated for over a decade. It ceased funding new projects in the late 1960s.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains publications originally held in the Ford Foundation's library and archives. The subject matter of the materials reflects the work of the Foundation, the Fund for Adult Education, and the Fund for the Advancement of Education.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged into four series:
1. Ford Foundation Staff Publications
Subseries 1: Books
Subseries 2: Articles and Reports
2. Ford Foundation Library Reference Materials
3. Fund for Adult Education (FAE) Publications
4. The Fund for the Advancement of Education (TFAE) Publications
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2013 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as part of Accession 2013:005.
Related Materials
Ford Foundation records, Publications (FA767) http://dimes.rockarch.org/FA767/collection
Ford Foundation records, Publications (Non-Grant Related), Accessions 2017:079 and 2017:089 (FA1394) http://dimes.rockarch.org/FA1394/collection
Ford Foundation records, Publications (Non-Grant Related), Accession 2017:050 (FA1304) http://dimes.rockarch.org/FA1304/collection
Ford Foundation; Adult education; Agriculture; Arts; Community development; Education; Fund for Adult Education; Humanities; International development; Philanthropy; Population; Television -- Educational; Urban development
- Ford Foundation Staff Publications, 1941-1993; 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged loosely alphabetically by last name of author. Ford Foundation staff author name is noted on each book's spine. "Staff:" in the folder title typically indicates there are multiple authors. The author's name after the colon denotes the Ford Foundation staff member(s) whose writing is included in the collaborative work.
  - Books, 1
    - Tecnologia de la Enseñanza, James W. Armsey and Norman C. Dahl, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Staff: Armsey and Dahl
    - Improving Management for More Effective Government: 50th Anniversary Lectures of the United States General Accounting Office, 1921-1971, Staff: David E. Bell (Box 1, Folder 2)
      From the Perspective of the Former Government Executive, Assessment of Efforts to Assist Underdeveloped Areas, Discussion, David E. Bell
    - Foreign Policy Decision Making: The New Dimensions, Staff: David E. Bell, 1973 May (Box 1, Folder 3)
      David Bell - Part of the UNA-USA Policy Panel on Foreign Policy Decision Making
    - American Indians and World War II: Toward a New Era in Indian Affairs, Alison Bernstein, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - The Antioch Review, Summer 1979 Volume 37, Number 3, Staff: Paul Bixler (Box 1, Folder 5)
      "Are You Glad to be Back, Jack?", Bixler
    - The Refounding of the College Board, 1948-1963: An Informal Commentary and Selected Papers, Frank Bowles, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Qualitative Aspects of Educational Planning, C. E. Beeby, Unesco: International Institute for Educational Planning (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Two school systems within one society, Frank Bowles
    - When the Marching Stopped: An Analysis of Black Issues in the '70s, A Publication of the National Urban League, Staff: Andrew F. Brimmer and Benjamin F. Payton (2 copies), 1973 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - The Strength of Government: The Godkin Lectures at Harvard University, McGeorge Bundy, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Whose Goals For American Higher Education?, American Council on Education, Edited by Charles G. Dobbins and Calvin B. T. Lee, Staff McGeorge Bundy, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Fresh Perspectives on Goals: In Praise of Candor, McGeorge Bundy
    - Bureaucratic Politics and Administration in Chile, Peter S. Cleaves, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Agriculture, Bureaucracy, and Military Government in Peru, Peter S. Cleaves and Martin J. Scurrah, Staff, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - The Disadvantaged: Challenge to Education, Mario D. Fantini and Gerald Weinstein, Staff: Fantini, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Staff: Fantini
    - Urban Leadership in the Sixties, James V. Cunningham, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - New York State and Private Higher Education: Report of the Select Committee on the Future of Private and Independent Higher Education in New York State, Staff: McGeorge Bundy, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Reconnection for Learning: A Community School System for New York City: Report of the Mayor's Advisory Panel on Decentralization of the New York Schools, Staff: McGeorge Bundy and Mitchell Sviridoff, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Designing Education for Tomorrow's Cities, Mario D. Fantini and Milton A. Young, Staff: Fantini, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Thesis: An Analysis of Agricultural Education, Training, and Personnel Requirements as a Basis for National Development in Burma, William Keith Gamble, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Legal Imperialism: American Lawyers and Foreign Aid in Latin America, James W. Gardner, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Earthkeeping: The War with Nature and a Proposal for Peace, Gordon Harrison, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      Signed by Gordon Harrison to David E. Bell
    - Universities...and Development Assistance Abroad, Edited by Richard A. Humphrey, American Council on Education, Staff: John F. Hilliard, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - The Third Century: Twenty-Six Prominent Americans Speculate on the Educational Future with an Essay by Nathan Glazer, Staff: Harold Howe II, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Education for Freedom, Robert M. Hutchins, 1941 (Box 4, Folder 23)
      Signed to Clarissa, February 10, 1943
    - The Selected Papers of Wolf Ladejinsky: Agrarian Reform as Unfinished Business, Editor, Louis J. Walinsky, Staff: Ladejinsky, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - The Contemporary University: USA, Edited by Robert S. Morrison, Staff: W. McNeil Lowry, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      The Arts, W. McNeil Lowry
    - The Challenge to American Foreign Policy, John J. McCloy, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Volume II - Supplement to the Composite Report of The President's Committee To Study the United States Military Assistance Program - Annexes, Staff: John J. McCloy, 1959 August 17 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Social Class and Social Policy, S. M. Miller and Frank Riessman, Staff: Miller, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 28)
      Staff: Miller
    - Connecting Worlds: A Survey of Developments in Educational Research, Robert G. Myers, 1980 June (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - A Prelude to War: Kennedy in Vietnam: American Vietnam Policy, 1960-1963, William J. Rust, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Conflict and Control in an African Trade Union, David R. Smock, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 31)
      Signed by David Smock to David E. Bell
    - The Politics of Pluralism: A Comparative Study of Lebanon and Ghana, David R. Smock and Audrey C. Smock, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 32)
      Signed to Doc from David and Audrey
    - The Search for National Integration in Africa, Edited by David R. Smock and Kwamena Bentsi-Enchill, Staff: Smock, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Work-Oriented General Education: A Proposal for Curriculum Development at the School Stage, Eugene Staley, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 34)
      With Compliments of the Authors and of the New Delhi Office of the Ford Foundation
    - Planning Occupational Education and Training for Development, Eugene Staley, 1970 March (Box 6, Folder 35)
    - The American Business Creed, Francis X. Sutton, Seymour E. Harris, Carl Kaysen, James Tobin, Staff: Sutton, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    - South Africa: Time Running Out, The Report of the Study Commission on U.S. Policy Toward Southern Africa, Staff: Franklin A. Thomas, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 37)
      Franklin A. Thomas, Chair, President, The Ford Foundation
    - Human Resources in India, George Tobias, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 38)
    - India's Manpower Strategy Revisited, 1947-1967, George Tobias and Robert S. Queener, 1968 November (Box 6, Folder 39)
    - A Life in Peace and War, Brian Urquhart, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - Ralph Bunche: An American Life, Brian Urquhart, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Learning to Be: The World of Education Today and Tomorrow, Frederick Champion Ward, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - International Commission on the Development of Education Report, Learning to Be, Staff: Frederick Champion Ward, 1972 May (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - Sources of Information in the Social Sciences: A Guide to the Literature, Carl M. White, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 44)
    - The Performance of Industrial Development Corporations: The Case of Jamaica, Stacey H. Widdicombe, Jr., 1972 (Box 8, Folder 45)
      Signed by Stacey Widdicombe to the Ford Foundation, 1973 January, Washington, D.C.
  - Articles and Reports, 2
    - Peter D. Bell, "The Ford Foundation as a Transnational Actor", 1971 (Box 9, Folder 46)
      Reprinted from International Organization Volume XXV, Number 3
    - Bernard Berelson, "Demographic Requirements of Fertility Control Technology: 15 Propositions," Program for the Introduction and Adaptation of Contraceptive Technology (PIACT) Papers, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 47)
    - Frank Bowles, "Educational Television 1955-1956: Condensed Report" (Box 9, Folder 48)
    - Frank Bowles, "A Report on the Test Cities Project, 1951-1956", 1956 May 15 (Box 9, Folder 49)
    - McGeorge Bundy, "Foreign Affairs and the Armed Forces", 1951 March 25 (Box 9, Folder 50)
      Submitted to the Woodrow Wilson Foundation
    - McGeorge Bundy, "Nuclear Weapons and Foreign Policy", 1956 (Box 9, Folder 51)
    - McGeorge Bundy, "McGeorge Bundy on the Bakke Case," The Atlantic, 1977 November (Box 9, Folder 52)
    - William J. Carmichael, "The Fiscal Structure of the Proposal," in What Price Economic Growth, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 53)
    - Fred E. Crossland, "The Push-Pull of Foundation Dollars" in the College Board Review, No. 90, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 54)
    - Edgar O. Edwards, Articles, Essays, and Publications, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 55)
    - Douglas Ensminger, "Complacency - The Greatest Danger," in Kurukshetra, 1955 June (Box 9, Folder 56)
    - Alvin C. Eurich, "A Foundation Looks at College Teaching by Television," The Journal of Educational Sociology, Special Issue: Television and College Teaching, 1958 May (Box 9, Folder 57)
    - Mario D. Fantini and Gerald Weinstein, "Toward a Contact Curriculum", undated (Box 9, Folder 58)
    - Mario Fantini and Gerald Weinstein, "Making Urban Schools Work: Social Realities and the Urban School", 1968 (Box 9, Folder 59)
    - Mario D. Fantini and Gerald Weinstein, "From the General Field: Reducing the Behavior Gap" in The Pedagogic Reporter, Vol. XIX, No. 4, American Association for Jewish Education, 1968 June (Box 9, Folder 60)
    - Afterword by Mario Fantini, Ocean Hill-Brownsville: A Case History of Schools in Crisis, 1969 (Box 9, Folder 61)
    - Fred Friendly, The Mayor's Advisory Task Force on CATV and Telecommunications: A Report on Cable Television and Cable Telecommunications in New York City, 1968 September 14 (Box 9, Folder 62)
    - George F. Gant, "A Note on Applications of Development Administration," in Public Policy, Harvard University, Volume XV, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 63)
    - Peter Hakim, "Nutrition and National Development: Establishing the Connection," MIT International Nutrition Planning Program, Discussion Papers No. 5, 1975 December (Box 9, Folder 64)
    - Henry Heald, "School Construction in New York City: The Report of the State Education Commissioner's Committee on Inquiry into Charges of Waste and Extravagance in the Construction of School Buildings in New York City," The University of the State of New York, State Education Department, Albany, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 65)
    - Henry Heald, "Meeting the Increasing Demand for Higher Education in New York State," A Report to the Governor and the Board of Regents, 1960 November (Box 9, Folder 66)
    - Henry Heald, "Meet the Press" Transcript, Vol. 4, No. 51, 1960 December 25 (Box 9, Folder 67)
    - Harold Howe II, New York State Regents Advisory Committee on Educational Leadership Reports, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 68)
    - Harold Howe II, R&D Funding Policies of the National Institute of Education: Review and Recommendations, Final Report of Consultants to the Director and the National Council on Educational Research, 1975 (Box 10, Folder 69)
    - Roger Kennedy, "Financial Problems of Foundations Today" and "Shareholder Responsibility in Institutional Investment: How the Ford Foundation Deals with Social Issues", 1975 (Box 10, Folder 70)
    - W. McNeil Lowry, "Patterns of Giving in the Arts and Humanities," Twelfth Biennial Conference on Charitable Foundations, 1975 May (Box 10, Folder 71)
    - Richard Magat, "Foundation Reporting," 9th Biennial Conference on Charitable Foundations, 1989 May (Box 10, Folder 72)
    - Edward J. Meade, Jr., Public Broadcasting for New Jersey Volume I, Governor's Commission on Public Broadcasting for New Jersey; "Lessons Learned: When a Foundation Goes to School;" "Is Law Polluting Our Schools?", 1968-1977 (Box 10, Folder 73)
    - Kirsten S. Moy, "Private Sector Development Organizations: A Directory," National Council for Urban Economic Development, 1984 June (Box 10, Folder 74)
    - Herbert Passin, "Writer and Journalist in the Transitional Society", 1962 (Box 10, Folder 75)
    - Gordon Perkin, "Contraceptive Development for Developing Countries: Unmet Needs", 1976 (Box 10, Folder 76)
    - George W. Perkin, "Population Policy and Programmes in South-east Asia: A Discussion of Limiting Factors," Advances in Fertility Control, Vol. 4, No. 3, 1969 September (Box 10, Folder 77)
    - Jeffrey M. Puryear, "Vocational Training and Earnings in Colombia: Does a SENA Effect Exist?, Comparative Education Review, Vol. 23, No. 2, 1979 June (Box 10, Folder 78)
    - Linda Redman, "Abortion, Contraception and Child Mental Health," Family Planning Perspectives, Volume 5, Number 2, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 79)
    - William S. Saint, Mão-de-Obra Volante Na Agricultura Brasileira: Uma Revisão da Bibliografia, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 80)
    - Donald F. Sandberg, "The Ford Foundation and Latin American Higher Education," Viewpoints on Education and Social Change in Latin America, University of Kansas, Occasional Publications Number Five, 1965 December (Box 10, Folder 81)
    - David R. Smock, "The Role of Anthropology in a Western Nigerian Resettlement Project", undated (Box 10, Folder 82)
    - Eugene Staley, "Toward a More Work-Oriented Schooling," Reprinted from Economic and Political Weekly, Vol. VII, Nos. 31-33, 1972 August (Box 10, Folder 83)
    - Mitchell Sviridoff, "Contradictions in Community Action," Psychiatry and Social Science Review, 1968 October (Box 10, Folder 84)
    - William O'Neill Sweeney, "Population Family Planning Media Communications in 25 Countries," A Synthesis of Population Communication Experience Paper 11, 1977 June (Box 10, Folder 85)
    - William O. Sweeney, "The Role of Communications in the Development Process," Teachers College Record, Vol. 76, No. 4, 1975 May (Box 10, Folder 86)
    - Clair Wilcox, "The Planning and Execution of Economic Development in Southeast Asia," Harvard University Center for International Affairs, Occasional Papers in International Affairs, Number 10, 1965 January (Box 10, Folder 87)
    - Louis Winnock, "A Towering Legacy Ends," New York Forum, 1988 June 24 (Box 10, Folder 88)
    - Thomas H. Wright, Jr., "Grantee Selection and Supervision: Legal Requirements and Practical Problems," 10th Biennial Charitable Foundations, undated (Box 10, Folder 89)
- Ford Foundation Library Reference Materials, 1948-2009; 2
  - Resources for the Future Annual Reports, 1954-1973 (Box 10, Folder 90-95, Box 11, Folder 96-107, Box 12, Folder 108-109)
  - Resources for the Future Annual Reports, 1975-1976 (Box 12, Folder 110-111)
  - Resources for the Future Newsletters, 1959-1969 (Box 12, Folder 112)
    Published 3 times a year
  - Resources for the Future, The First Five Years, Annual Reports, 1955-1959 (Box 12, Folder 113)
  - Resources for the Future Annual Reports, 1960-1964 (Box 13, Folder 114)
  - Resources for the Future, Inc. Annual Report, 1952-1953 (Box 13, Folder 115)
  - The Nation Looks at Its Resources: Report of the Mid-Century Conference on Resources for the Future, 1954 (Box 13, Folder 116)
  - Soil Conservation in Perspective by R. Burnell Held and Marion Clawson, 1965 (Box 13, Folder 117)
  - Encounter (London, periodicals), 1961 June-1969 November (Box 13, Folder 118, Box 14, Folder 119-130, Box 15, Folder 131-144, Box 16, Folder 145-159, Box 17, Folder 160-172, Box 18, Folder 173-187, Box 19, Folder 188-202, Box 20, Folder 203)
    Missing a few volumes
  - Assorted Encounter Pamphlets, 1960-1964 (Box 20, Folder 204-211)
    Pamphlet Numbers: 2, 4, 5, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12
  - Encounter, Creative Theological Scholarship, Vol. 28, No. 3, 1967 (Box 20, Folder 212)
  - Continental Classroom - An Analysis of Reactions to "Probability and Statistics:" A Research Report Prepared For The Roper Public Opinion Research Center, Williams College, International Research Associates, Inc., 1961 July (Box 20, Folder 213)
  - The Technology of Instruction in Mexican Universities by Noel McGinn with Russell G. Davis and Richard G. King, Education and World Affairs, 1968 December (Box 20, Folder 214)
  - Coping with the Oil Crisis: French and German Experiences, Horst Mendershausen, 1976 (Box 20, Folder 215)
  - New Deal Planning: The National Resources Planning Board, Marion Clawson, 1981 (Box 20, Folder 216)
  - Forced Labor in the "People's Democracies," Richard K. Carlton, Editor, 1955 (Box 21, Folder 217)
  - The Housing Problem in the Soviet Union, Timothy Sosnovy, Research Program on the USSR, 1954 (Box 21, Folder 218)
  - The Professional School and World Affairs: Report of the Task Force on Medicine and Public Health, A Report from Education and World Affairs, 1967 July (Box 21, Folder 219)
  - The Professional School and World Affairs: Report of the Task Force on Business Administration and Public Administration, A Report from Education and World Affairs, 1967 May (Box 21, Folder 220)
  - The Professional School and World Affairs: Report of the Task Force on Agriculture and Engineering, A Report from Education and World Affairs, 1967 June (Box 21, Folder 221)
  - The Professional School and World Affairs: Report of the Task Force on Education, A Report from Education and World Affairs, 1967 October (Box 21, Folder 222)
  - Library Borrower Cards and Catalog Cards for The Teaching of Economics in Mexico, Blanca Petricioli, undated (Box 21, Folder 223)
  - Report of the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees, 1969 May 28 (Box 21, Folder 224)
  - The Uprooted Strike Root: Report of Progress from October 1st, 1952 to March 31st, 1953, Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees (with photographs), 1953 April 15 (Box 21, Folder 225)
  - Educational Facilities Laboratories Publications List, 1964 August 4 (Box 21, Folder 226)
  - East European Fund, Inc. Reports, Newsletters, and Papers, 1953-1955 (Box 21, Folder 227)
  - Political Controls in the Soviet Army, Research Program on the USSR (East European Fund), 1954 (Box 21, Folder 228)
  - Logic and Dialectic in the Soviet Union by Alexander Philipov, Research Program on the USSR (East European Fund), 1952 (Box 21, Folder 229)
  - Music Under the Soviets: The Agony of an Art, Andrey Olkhovsky (East European Fund), 1955 (Box 22, Folder 230)
  - Archaeology in the USSR, Mikhail Miller, Research Program on the USSR (East European Fund), 1956 (Box 22, Folder 231)
  - Dostoyevski in Russian Literary Criticism, 1846-1956, Vladimir Seduro (East European Fund), 1957 (Box 22, Folder 232)
  - The Byelorussian Theater and Drama, Vladimir Seduro, Research Program on the USSR (East European Fund), 1955 (Box 22, Folder 233)
  - Comedy in the Soviet Theater, Peter Yershov, Research Program on the USSR (East European Fund), 1956 (Box 22, Folder 234)
  - Soviet Theaters, 1917-1941: A Collection of Articles, Research Program on the USSR (East European Fund), 1954 (Box 22, Folder 235)
  - The Northern Sea Route and the Economy of the Soviet North, Constantine Krypton, Research Program on the USSR (East European Fund), 1956 (Box 22, Folder 236)
  - The Soviet Secret Police, Simon Wolin and Robert M. Slusser (East European Fund), 1957 (Box 23, Folder 237)